<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>subsymbol.org (linguistics)</title><link>http://www.subsymbol.org/</link><description></description><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2014 11:10:18 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Addresses and Contents</title><link>http://www.subsymbol.org/posts/addresses-and-contents.html</link><dc:creator>L. Amber Wilcox-O'Hearn</dc:creator><description>&lt;div class="section" id="what-are-we-naming"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What are we naming?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The name of the song is called "Haddocks' Eyes."'&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;'Oh, that's the name of the song, is it?' Alice said, trying to feel interested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;'No, you don't understand,' the Knight said, looking a little vexed. 'That's what the name is called. The name really is "The Aged Aged Man."'&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;'Then I ought to have said "That's what the song is called"?' Alice corrected herself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;'No, you oughtn't: that's quite another thing! The song is called "Ways and Means": but that's only what it's called, you know!'&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;'Well, what is the song, then?' said Alice, who was by this time completely bewildered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;'I was coming to that,' the Knight said. 'The song really is "A-sitting On A Gate": and the tune's my own invention.'&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.alice-in-wonderland.net/books/2chpt8.html"&gt;Alice Through the Looking Glass&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="mutability-applies-to-content"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Mutability applies to content&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been designing a system that seeks to change the way we name our data:
instead of naming the hierarchical way, using directories (or folders), it will name the category way, using tags.
Because the system needed an ID for every file it tagged, and perhaps for no other good reason than that I am fond of content-based hashing,
I chose to use a content-based hash for the IDs.
However, this ID is not a good match for mutable files.
I had been putting off thinking about how to handle mutable files, figuring I could add that functionality later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was finally ready to confront mutable files, I realised that I was running up against a fundamental issue:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="people-often-conflate-addresses-with-contents-when-naming-things"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;People often conflate addresses with contents when naming things&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take for example the problem of citation.
If you cite a book or a research paper, then what you are citing is the contents.
When we first started wanting to cite URLs, we treated them as though we were addressing content, but we aren't.
URLs point to content that can change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, this issue shows up in many areas of computer science whenever we use references.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="filesystems"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Filesystems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a filesystem, we usually refer to files by their paths.
The relationships between paths, addresses (inodes), and contents are shown here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-0dFaK3jKirQ/U78BnodwrUI/AAAAAAAACPs/mGzaDJfLZk4/w426-h376-no/name_triangle.png" src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-0dFaK3jKirQ/U78BnodwrUI/AAAAAAAACPs/mGzaDJfLZk4/w426-h376-no/name_triangle.png"&gt;&lt;p&gt;That is, a pathname refers to a single inode, but not necessarily vice versa.
An inode has exactly one set of contents, but those contents may be replicated in many inodes in the system.
I didn't recognise at first that the problem of mutable and immutable files is the distinction between addresses and contents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as file systems go, I don't know of any that make the distinction between contents and addresses, except Tahoe-LAFS.
The reference to an immutable file in Tahoe is content based for integrity and deduplication.
The reference to a mutable file just specifies a unique "slot".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've decide to follow this paradigm in Protagonist.
Both addresses and contents should be eligible for tagging.
Tagging the box will use the inode.
Tagging the contents will use the hash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- The fact that we make extensive use of links in our systems attests the fact that hierarchies are not a great model for naming things. --&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>linguistics</category><category>names</category><category>storage</category><guid>http://www.subsymbol.org/posts/addresses-and-contents.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2014 21:42:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Literally ironic semantic shifts are actually very typical</title><link>http://www.subsymbol.org/posts/201404literally-ironic-semantic-shifts-are.html</link><dc:creator>L. Amber Wilcox-O'Hearn</dc:creator><description>&lt;div class="document" id="literally-ironic-semantic-shifts-are-ironically-very-typical"&gt;   &lt;p&gt;I recently saw a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.npr.org/2014/04/23/306238447/new-browser-plug-in-would-literally-annihilate-this-headline"&gt;story about a whimsical browser plug-in written by Mike Lazer-Walker&lt;/a&gt;(incidentally, a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.hackerschool.com/blog/30-words-are-hard"&gt;Hacker Schooler&lt;/a&gt;), that substitutes all occurrences of the word 'literally' with the word 'figuratively'. I posted it with (almost) no comment on Facebook, to which the only response was from a Waterloo friend, who actually found the substitution annoying, because, he argued, 'figuratively' is not what is usually meant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course, he is right about that. 'Literally', like 'very', 'really', 'truly', and in some cases 'actually' &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://www.subsymbol.org/posts/201404literally-ironic-semantic-shifts-are.html#id3" id="id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;, share a common semantic shift. They all originally meant something like 'do not take the following as exaggeration or metaphor' (insofar as any language use can be non-metaphorical), and have all become intensifiers. This is, of course, somewhat ironic (in the situational sense of 'ironic', which is neither the literary sense, nor the emerging sense of 'not what I wanted' &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://www.subsymbol.org/posts/201404literally-ironic-semantic-shifts-are.html#id4" id="id2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don't cringe when I hear 'very', except insofar as it is often vacuous. That I do cringe on hearing 'literally' used as an intensifier is probably because, unlike 'very', the current use which is very &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=very"&gt;old&lt;/a&gt;, this meaning of 'literally' emerged in my adulthood, and so it sounds unnatural to me. When wearing my linguist hat, I like to embrace diversity and change, rather than taking the stance that my dialect is 'correct'. The strongest stance I can fairly take is that in &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; dialect, the new meaning is unacceptable, or that using this meaning has certain social implications about the speaker.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But rather than taking the plug-in to be suggesting an actual solution, I take it in the spirit of Mark Twain's advice: 'Substitute 'damn' every time you're inclined to write 'very;' your editor will delete it and the writing will be just as it should be.' Once the reader or writer sees 'figuratively', the appropriate transformation should be more readily obvious.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;More likely, it is simply an elaborate joke made by a clever person while exploring how to write plug-ins. In any case, I liked the idea, both for its wit, and for the other fun linguistics ideas it points to, including, for example, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.gizoogle.net/tranzizzle.php?search=www.subsymbol.org&amp;amp;se=Go+Git+Dis+Shiznit"&gt;tranzizzle&lt;/a&gt; (hat tip to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.gizoogle.net/tranzizzle.php?search=www.cs.cmu.edu%2F~nasmith&amp;amp;se=Go+Git+Dis+Shiznit"&gt;Noah Smizzle&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The question I am left with is, given this development, what word do I use &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt; if I want the literal meaning of literal?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id3" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://www.subsymbol.org/posts/201404literally-ironic-semantic-shifts-are.html#id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;'Actually' is often used to make a contrast.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id4" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://www.subsymbol.org/posts/201404literally-ironic-semantic-shifts-are.html#id2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;See this comic: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://theoatmeal.com/comics/irony"&gt;http://theoatmeal.com/comics/irony&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>linguistics</category><guid>http://www.subsymbol.org/posts/201404literally-ironic-semantic-shifts-are.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 26 Apr 2014 22:06:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>